ORIGINAL STORY BY NATSU HYUUGA
（原作：日向夏）
THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
I'm sorry to bother you with this, but…
发生了一件有点麻烦的事
He always brings annoying work without asking for permission.
明明总是把麻烦事直接送上门的
This is very unlike Sir Jinshi.
还真不像壬氏大人会说的话
-What is it? -The thing is…
-怎么了吗？ -其实是…
It's a troublesome affair happening to a friend of a friend.
我的熟人的熟人那边起了争端
A court purveyor goldsmith has passed away
宫廷御用的雕金师还没把技术
without teaching his apprentice sons his techniques.
传给身为徒弟的儿子们 就过世了
Some of those techniques have never been shared with anyone.
在这当中包含了绝不外传的技术
So you want me to figure out the secret technique of the goldsmith.
也就是说 只要弄清楚 他的秘传技术是什么就行了吧？
You say it like it's easy.
你说得倒简单
And you seem more enthusiastic than usual.
话说 你怎么好像很有兴致的样子？
Is that so?
是吗？
The goldsmith had three sons, who were all his apprentices.
雕金师有三个儿子 都是他的徒弟
One of those sons will be the purveyor
在他们的父亲过世后
now that the father has passed away.
大家都说其中一位会成为御用工匠
In their father's will,
其父亲留下的遗言中
he had written down how his possessions would be split.
写下了要分送的遗物
The first son will get the outbuilding studio.
长子是别栋的工作小屋
The second son will get furniture with goldsmith decorations.
次子是附有雕金装饰的家具
The third son will get a goldfish bowl.
么子则是金鱼缸
And he left behind the words,
还留下一句话
"You all should have tea together just like the old times."
“你们像以前一样开茶会就好了”
That was it.
就说了这些
Tea?
茶会？
That's got to mean something.
真是耐人寻味的遗言呢
Should we take those words at face value,
不知道是字面上的意思
or does it mean something else?
还是有别有含意呢？
Seems like the sons have no idea either.
听了遗言的当事人们也一头雾水
And there seems to be an imbalance in how the possessions were split.
是说 遗物的分配差异很大呢
A shed, furniture, and a goldfish bowl.
小屋、家具和金鱼缸
The youngest seems to be getting the short end of the stick.
怎么看都是辈分越小的越吃亏
What type of goldfish can it be?
都是些什么样的东西呢？
I haven't heard the details about that. However…
他并没有说得很详细 不过…
If you want to know more, here's the address.
要是有兴趣的话 这是住所位置
"If you're curious, you should pay them a visit." That's what he said.
“要是有兴趣 就去看看吧” 他是这么说的
He's prepared.
准备真是周全
Seems like he knew the whole time what was about to happen.
好像一开始就知道会是如此
How interesting.
真有意思
Could I take time off to pay them a visit tomorrow?
若是明天能给我些时间的话…
Looks like I'd get more work once I'm back.
看来 回来之后工作又要增加了
Oh, is that…
咦？
His name was Basen, if I remember correctly.
我记得 他说自己叫马闪
Just like before, you're my "personal servant."
就跟之前一样 你是我的婢女
Don't move around on your own.
不准擅自行动啊
Understood, sir.
我明白
Just like before.
“就跟之前一样”
He only talks when he needs to.
没必要就不说话
Seems like he dislikes me.
看来他似乎不太喜欢我
As long as he doesn't do me any harm, it's fine.
只要不危害我也无妨吧
Yes. Sir Basen, correct?
是马闪大人 对吧？
I was told you are coming.
事情我已经听说了
Oh, that belonged to my father.
哦 那是我父亲的东西
He had a hobby of collecting odd things.
他的兴趣是收集奇怪的物品
I see.
这样啊
-That's the studio? -Yes.
-那个就是工作小屋吗？ -对
But we mostly do our work at the main house.
话虽如此 现在都在正屋里工作
Now, it's a place where the workers have tea.
那儿就变成了工匠们喝茶的地方
Come in.
请进
Brothers, they're here.
哥哥 他们来了
-Hello. -Thank you for coming.
-哦 -特地跑一趟 辛苦了
It seems like the boy that showed us around
他说哥哥
is the youngest brother.
也就是说 带路的是么子了
The furniture is arranged strangely.
这家具的配置还真特别
Hey!
喂！
He's right.
的确
Having furniture in the middle like this must be annoying.
一般要是把家具放在正中央 会很挡路吧？
But the room doesn't look bad.
即使如此 屋子看起来感觉并不坏
Probably because the tables are placed in a uniform way,
可能是因为桌子的配置 有种微妙的整体感
and because the cabinet is decorated.
以及五斗柜相当别致的关系吧？
Goldsmith decorations on the corners.
边角嵌着金属装饰
Keyholes on the top three rows, and the bottom center shelf.
最上层三排和下层中央抽屉的锁孔
The bottom shelf is decorated with a different kind of metal.
只有这些地方使用不同的金属
It's fixed to the floor so it can't move?
这个柜子锁死在地板上了？
Hey, that's mine.
喂 这是我的东西
You can look, but you can't touch.
看看是无妨 可不准碰啊
The furniture was passed on to the second son.
说起来 次子分到的遗物是家具
If that cabinet is one of the pieces of furniture,
如果是指这个五斗柜的话
then he must be the second son.
这个男人就是次子吧
That means this tall man is the oldest son.
那么 那位高个子的男人就是长子了
The window is placed oddly too.
窗子的位置也很奇特
A long window in a Western style.
采用西式风格 奇妙的长形窗子
This home is made to let in plenty of sunlight,
特别造了这种能引进大量日光的设计
but the large chestnut tree outside is blocking the sun.
外头的大栗子树却挡住了太阳
The light entering here is filtered through the tree..
进到屋里的只有枝叶间的日光
This spot is the only area with enough sunlight.
只有这儿才能完全照到阳光
This mark…
这个痕迹
Was something placed here for a long time?
是有什么东西长时间放在这儿吗？
So you'll really figure out our father's message?
你们真的能弄明白吧？ 我父亲留下来的东西
Well, that's…
这个…
I couldn't say until you tell us more details.
我们得先听听更详细的状况 否则也无法断言
You've already heard it all.
就跟你们听说的一样
Our father left us without teaching us the secret technique.
父亲还未传授秘传技术 就这么过世了
Instead, he left behind this shed for me.
然后 留给我的就是这间小屋
For me, this cabinet.
我是这个五斗柜
And this bowl was for me.
我拿到的是这个
It's made of high-quality glass.
用高级玻璃制成的？
I thought that the goldfish bowl would be wood or porcelain.
说是金鱼缸 还以为是木制 再好也不过是陶制
In that case, all these possessions all hold their own value.
这样的话 三人拿到的遗物可说是各有价值
What was Dad thinking?
阿爹到底在想什么？
He left this behind,
好不容易拿到遗物
but there's only one key and it doesn't fit in the hole.
却只有一把钥匙 还放不进锁孔
The key doesn't fit?
放不进锁孔吗？
I think this key is for this central shelf.
我想 这把应该是中间抽屉的钥匙
But it doesn't fit.
但是放不进锁孔
The top three shelves all open with the same key,
上面三个抽屉 应该能用同一把钥匙打开
but I can't find the key in question.
但最重要的钥匙不知道在哪儿
What's the point of receiving this if I can't use it?
拿到这样的东西 根本毫无用处
Same goes for me.
我也是啊
I have this shed, but I can't move the cabinet. It's in the way.
虽说拿到了小屋 但五斗柜动不了 只会碍事
Dad caused us a lot of trouble.
徒增麻烦罢了
I think…
阿爹…
I think Dad wanted us to…
我想阿爹是希望我们…
You're lucky, you know?
你可好了
You received something you can sell on the spot.
拿到的是可以马上变卖的东西
Yeah.
对啊
If you sell that, you could live off of that money for a while.
就算是那种东西 卖了钱也能暂时不愁吃穿呢
What was wrong with Dad?
真是搞不懂阿爹
What's the point of having tea together after all this time?
现在要大家开茶会 是能做什么？
Now, what shall we do?
哎呀 该怎么办呢？
Looks like the relationship between the brothers
看来么子和两个哥哥
is quite strained.
关系很淡薄呢
Cut it out, you three!
你们三个 给我收敛点
Don't embarrass yourselves in front of the guests.
在客人面前如此 真是丢脸
I'm so sorry.
让你们见笑了
I don't know when they became this way.
不知何时开始变成了这样子
The two oldest sons became cynical and bitter,
长子和次子都变得尖酸刻薄
and the youngest can't speak up for himself.
老么也不敢说出自己的意见
This is why my husband
就是因为这样
worried for them until his very last breath.
我丈夫才会到最后都放不下心
Seems like parents
为人父母的
will always worry for their children, no matter how old they are.
无论孩子多大 大概都操心不完吧
Please have some tea. Enjoy.
请用茶 我先告辞了
Everyone changed positions to sit down.
大家都刻意移动位置才坐下
They must have designated seats.
看来座位是固定的
They probably don't sit in front of the window out of habit.
是因为习惯而避开窗前的位置吗？
There's sunlight coming through the window at this time of day.
这个时间 日光正好从窗子照进来
If the light stretched out a bit more, it might hit the cabinet.
日光再长一点 应该能照到五斗柜
But there was no sun damage on the cabinet.
但五斗柜上并没有日晒的痕迹
Sun damage?
日晒的痕迹？
Hey.
喂
The sun doesn't hit this area for a long time.
日光照进来的时间并不长
There's something stuffed inside.
里面好像塞着什么
Did you figure something out?
知道些什么了吗？
I thought he reminded me of someone.
我想说是像谁呢
He looks just like Gaoshun!
这家伙很像高顺啊
So?
所以？
The shelf in the middle with the lock doesn't open, right?
有锁的中间抽屉打不开 对吧？
It used to open years ago.
以前有打开过
But as Dad added goldsmith decorations,
但父亲做了些加工后
it got sealed shut.
就打不开了
There's only one key?
钥匙只有一把吗？
Just this one. Dad said
只有一把 阿爹这家伙
if we break the lock, whatever's inside will break too.
他还说如果把锁弄坏 里面的东西也会坏掉
So I can't force it open.
所以也没办法用蛮力打开
The three possessions passed onto the three brothers.
兄弟三人分配到不同的遗物
The shed. The cabinet. The goldfish bowl.
小屋、五斗柜 和金鱼缸
The cabinet locked in position to the shed.
小屋中固定着五斗柜
A lock that doesn't open on the cabinet. Also…
五斗柜有打不开的锁 还有…
"You all should have tea together just like the old times."
“你们像以前一样开茶会就好了”
Could it be…?
难道说…
Excuse me. Could it be that this goldfish bowl was
请问 这个鱼缸原本是
decorated on that shelf?
放在那边的架子上 对吧？
Yes, that's right.
对 是这样没错
We used to place it here with a goldfish inside.
以前里面有养过金鱼 并放在这儿
It would die if it gets too cold,
因为天一冷 鱼就会冻死
so in winter, it was only here when we had tea, during warm hours.
所以只有冬天茶会时 会趁温暖的白天放在这儿
Around this time of day, actually.
其实就差不多是这个时候
The past few years,
最近几年来
we haven't had goldfish, so it just became a decoration.
都没有养金鱼 所以就成了摆饰
Hey, you!
喂 我说你啊
I'm going to go ask for some water.
我去要点水来
She's moving around without permission again.
又自己擅自行动了
This is how you added the water back then?
以前是像这样装水 对吧？
Yes.
没有错
So that the painting would face this way.
图案正好朝向这儿
I knew it.
果然
Hey! What is this?
咦？这是什么？
Don't touch it!
别碰！
I'm sorry. If you look at the light, you'll go blind.
抱歉 但如果照到眼睛会失明的
Also, you're in the way, so please move.
还有你很碍事 请离远一点
Otherwise, it won't unlock.
否则会开不了锁的
The sun hid behind the chestnut tree.
太阳似乎被栗子树挡住了
It's hot. And it smells strange…
很烫 还有股奇怪的味道
Hey, what's the point of all this?
喂 这有什么意义？
Please open this shelf with your key from before.
请用先前的钥匙打开这个抽屉吧
-I told you, it doesn't open! -Go ahead.
-我说过放不进去了 -请吧
What does this mean?
这是怎么回事？
Could it be that
你们的父亲
your father often had anemia and stomach pains?
是不是经常犯贫血和腹痛？
Yes, he did.
正是如此
What about nausea or depression?
此外 是不是还患反胃和忧郁？
He had those too.
是这样没错
I don't know much about goldsmithing.
虽然我不是很懂雕金术
Do you use solder in the studio as well?
但你们这儿有用到焊料吗？
Yes, we do.
有在用
What does this mean?
怎么回事？
I only followed your father's wishes
我只是照着遗言
to have tea together, just like the old times.
“你们像以前一样开茶会就好了”
It's mold to make a key.
这是制作钥匙的铸模
Can I remove this from the mold?
我能将这个取出吗？
Oh… Sure.
哦 好
It's still a little warm, and soft.
还有点热度 而且很柔软
The metal stuck inside the keyhole must have melted from the heat
应该是塞在锁孔里的金属遇热熔化
and poured into the mold below and hardened.
流入下方的铸模后成型的吧？
-It's open! -What's inside?
-打开了 -里面是什么？
What the hell is this?
这是什么啊？
This blue crystal
这个蓝色结晶
is the same one decorated by the front door.
应该和玄关装饰是同样的东西
Damn it! What was the point of playing nice?
可恶 什么跟大家和睦相处？
All we did was get pulled into Dad's little tricks for the last time!
结果只是被阿爹恶作剧一场 就结束了嘛！
So sick of this.
真是忍无可忍了
Lead and tin?
铅和锡？
"Skills should be acquired by observing."
“偷师学艺”
A craftsman client used to say this often.
以前有个工匠气质的客人 说过这种话
I took those words to heart
结果我把这句话当真
and infused Old Man's medicinal herbs by copying him
拿了老爹采来的药草 有样学样地煎煎看
and poisoned myself.
然后就中毒了
Listen before watching, all right?
动手前先问过我 好吗？
That's what he said to me then.
我也是受过这种教训呢
Only the youngest son understood his late father's message,
恐怕 能了解过世父亲用意的
it seems.
只有么子吧？
Solder melts at a lower temperature than its original metals
据说 焊料是将数种金属混合后
when it is mixed with various types of metal.
让每种金属的 熔化温度变得比原本更低
Out of the three metal chunks, two are lead and tin.
三块东西中的两种是铅和锡
What if combining a third type of metal
若是和第三种金属结合
could create a whole new metal?
做出来的新金属会如何呢？
Despite being exposed to the heat of the light aggregated by the bowl,
再者 用金鱼缸 集中的日光能有多热先不谈
it wasn't exposed to the heat for long.
照射的时间也并不长
That means the melting point is that low.
仅仅如此 熔化的温度可说是相当低
The different sizes of the shelves may be indicating the mixing ratio.
大小各异的抽屉 应该也是为了提示混合的比例
But that's not for me to say.
不过 这些应该没必要说了
What kind of will is this? Let's go.
什么遗言嘛 走吧
I shouldn't have expected anything of Dad.
真不该对阿爹有什么期待
Wait, Brothers!
等一下 哥哥！
-What? -These aren't tricks.
-干嘛？ -这不是恶作剧
So what is it, then?
那是怎么样？
Dad wanted us to be close again.
父亲的遗言
That's why he left behind this message!
果然还是希望我们兄弟能和睦相处
-What? -That's why…
-什么？ -所以我…
I want to continue working with you both!
我今后也想继续和哥哥们一起工作
You want to work with us?
一起？跟我们？
Don't make us laugh. We're not like you.
别说笑了 我们才不一样
You have talent.
因为你独具天分
That's why Dad doted on you.
所以阿爹才会特别疼你
That's not true!
不是这样的
Dad trusted you two.
阿爹也很信赖哥哥们啊
Dad always used to say to me,
他总是跟我说
Brother Chan is always calm,
长兄不论何时都很冷静
and is always accurate with detailed work.
能够做好需要细心的工作
Because you don't make mistakes, he can trust you with any task.
因为不会出错 所以什么都能拜托你
Brother Tsu is good at capturing people's hearts.
次兄非常擅于掳获人心
Being able to become friends with anyone
能够和任何人打成一片
is a skill that you should be proud of.
这是哥哥值得骄傲的才能啊
Dad regarded us all in the same way.
阿爹对我们是一视同仁的
That's what I think, at least.
至少 我是这么想的
-Excuse us. -Oh, I'm sorry.
-抱歉 -啊 对不起
A father, huh?
父亲啊…
I wouldn't know anything about that.
算了 跟我没关系
Thank you very much!
非常感谢你们
I'll just leave them with this.
不过 有件事必须说一声
Hey!
喂！
In The Verdigris House at the pleasure district,
花街有间叫绿青馆的店家
there is an apothecary named Luomen.
里面有位名叫罗门的药师
He's a very skilled doctor as well.
他的医术十分了得
Please give him a visit if you're not feeling well.
若你的身体有恙 请务必拜访
Yes, I will.
好
Thank you for your help the other day.
前几天的事情 谢了
It was very interesting.
哎呀 变成了很有意思的结果呢
It seems as if
那三个兄弟当中
the youngest was the most capable out of the three brothers.
最出色的果然是么子啊
You must've known that, Sir General.
军师大人应该早就知道了吧？
The youngest became even more skilled after that affair.
在这之后 据说么子终于展现出实力
He'll become the successor and create metalworks for the court.
成为了继任者 在宫廷里面展现精湛的工艺
And the two eldest
长子和次子
will no longer work as craftsmen after this incident.
在这次事件后 似乎就不再当工匠了
-Why is that? -It's nothing bad.
-怎么会？ -怎么？不是坏事吧？
They took their late father's words to heart,
他们将亡父的遗言铭记在心
it looks like.
这样说吧
The eldest will manage sales.
长子负责经商管理
The second son will be the salesman.
次子则是开拓通路
They'll continue to support the family business in different ways.
他们用不同的方式 各自继续支持着家业
In other words,
换句话说
they all settled down in roles they're suited for.
就是找到了适材适用的位置
I don't know what happened in that mansion.
不知道在那宅邸发生了甚么事
I'm sure the Apothecary knows, and will keep quiet.
那个药师姑娘 一定是知情不报吧
The late goldsmith's work was really magnificent.
最后得说 前任雕金师的手艺真是出色
It was a simple metal fitting,
虽然只是个金属配件
but using that as decoration for ritual goods
但用在祭器上
will be beautiful.
一定十分相称吧
That's true.
的确是呢
What an unlikeable man.
真是令人厌恶的男人
He knows that ritual goods have nothing to do with my position.
他明明知道以我的立场 跟祭器应该一点关系都没有
-Why did you, Sir General… -It's nothing.
-为何军师大人对工匠… -没什么
I just felt it was a waste to neglect a hidden talent like that.
我只是觉得就这样埋没人才太可惜了
It doesn't matter who's older.
跟兄友弟恭毫无关系
We should recognize great talents.
既然有才能 就应该要好好提拔
He's right.
他说的有道理
Lakan is a sleazy man,
罗汉虽然是个怪人
but he's good at finding people's talent.
但他很有发掘人才的眼光
That power got him to the position he is in now.
也可说是因为这种领导力 让他爬到了现在的地位
Speaking of,
话说回来
I'd like to hear more of what you discussed before.
你之前说的事情 我对后续有些好奇
What do you mean?
之前说了什么事情？
The story about the courtesan.
之前说过关于娼妓的事情
Oh, you mean, how to decrease the scarcity value of a courtesan?
哦 你是说 降低娼妓稀少价值的方法吗？
You should ask
那种事情
someone who's well-versed in that world.
去问熟知那个世界的人会更快哦
Oh, it's already time.
哎呀 时间不早了
My men will yell at me if I stay for too long.
再待下去的话 部下会生气的
Please give this to your live-in maidservants.
请把这个交给你的贴身侍女吧
It's not too sweet. It's easy to drink.
不会太甜 也很容易入口
I'll see you tomorrow!
那么 明天见了
-Sir Jinshi. -Yeah?
-壬氏大人 -怎样？
I'm sorry to bother you after a long day.
虽然您很累了 但是…
Did you call for me?
您找我吗？
Do you know much about makeup?
你了解化妆吗？
I have the basic skills.
嗯 基本上会吧
In that case… Will you put makeup on me?
那么 你能替我化妆吗？
What?
什么？
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "A Jaunt Around Town."
下一集 《游览街市》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易